# **RUTH G. CIRILLO**

Front End Developer • ruthcirillo.info • ruthcirillo@outlook.com

#### **SUMMARY**

A seasoned front end developer experienced in creating multi-browser compatible web applications. I own the HTML, CSS, and JavaScript development of modern web applications often serving as the bridge between the technical and the artistic worlds. I am curious, self-motivated, and willing to explore new technologies – especially one that creates an inclusive and barrier free world.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Senior Interactive Developer at Publicis Sapient

11/2014 to Present

09/2009 to 09/2012

Develop clickable prototypes from visual designs and wireframes using HTML, CSS and JavaScript. Write and integrate presentation layer code with Content Management Systems (Drupal, Adobe Experience Manager, or WordPress). Work within frameworks (React, Bootstrap) to create responsive layouts. Build new UI patterns while also refactoring older ones. Work closely with back-end developers to ensure integrity of the interface throughout development life-cycle. Integrate backend services to front end templates. Manage front end assets using Gulp.js, Grunt.js, Node Package Manager (NPM) and Bower. Write test scripts using Selenium WebDriver, Java and TestNG. Ensure front end code meets accessibility criteria by testing application using Wave browser extension, JAWS and Voice Over. Update design documents such as wireframes and visual mockups.

#### Key contributions:

- Reduced feature development time by implementing block element modifier (BEM) methodology in template files and SASS files.
- Create an inventory of components in Confluence to define the standards and guidelines of use, style, and BEM classes for each element which resulted in common language used among developers, testers, product managers and visual designers.
- Create a short checklist of accessibility criteria for developers and testers to use as a supplement when testing with the WAVE Chrome extension.
- Won "The Half Smoke: the person who packs a punch and shows up extra prepared" award in March 2021. In less than a week, implemented responsive design on an existing application and added Babel.js to compile ES6 scripts so the site can work in IE Edge. Yes, IE.

## **User Interface Designer at SAIC**

02/2014 to 11/2014

Collaborated with product manager and business analysts to define user interface requirements. Designed and communicated conceptual solutions created in Photoshop with

annotations. Translated visual designs and wireframes into HTML, CSS and JavaScript adhering to approved design and business specifications.

## Key contributions:

- Documented the application's visual styles and shared components in team's SharePoint page.
- Created UI pattern library and interaction guidelines based on approved business rules.

## **User Interface Designer at Serco North America**

05/2013 to 01/2014

• Contract and role were transitioned to SAIC on 2/2014.

## Front End Developer at CGI Federal

09/2012 to 05/2013

Implemented Bootstrap framework into existing web application.

## Key contributions:

 Accomplished zero defects related to Section 508 Compliance as reported in VPAT by correct use of HTML elements, aria labels and landmarks, and CSS.

## **SKILLS**

## Front End Development

 HTML, CSS, CSS preprocessors: SASS, LESS, JavaScript (jQuery, Vanilla JS, ES6), Frameworks: Bootstrap, React JS

## **User Experience**

• UI Design, Wireframing, Sketching, Style Guide creation

## Tools

• Git, SVN, Node Package Manager (NPM), Gulp JS, Grunt JS, Jaws, Voice Over, Wave toolbar, Sketch, InVision, Balsamiq, Axure RP, Adobe Creative Cloud

#### **EDUCATION**

## George Mason University, Fairfax, VA

- Earned 42 credit hours in Information Technology between 8/2004 to 12/2006.
- B.S. in Health, Fitness and Recreation Resources, May 2002.

# Workshops

- "User Experience (UX) Design Training for Successful Software Development" provided by Learning Tree, January 2019.
- "User Experience Design Bootcamp" provided by General Assembly, January 2019.